This land of ours, its mountains and valleys, fields and forests, a place to live, a place to work, a place to enjoy.
But it's much more than that.
Our landscape teaches us things as well.
All around us, there's a vast repository of knowledge and every day brings surprising new discoveries.
From Darwin to robot farmers, science and our landscape have gone hand-in-hand.
In this edition of Countryfile, we'll be looking at how our landscape has shaped science, and how science has shaped our landscape.
And where better than this, Wytham Woods in Oxfordshire.
It's probably the most studied stretch of woodland anywhere in the world, and I'll be catching up with scientists who have turned Wytham Woods into a living laboratory.
And we'll be looking back at some of the best science to have featured on Countryfile.
Like the time Matt got into a tight spot, beloved of an 18th century naturalist.
And he believed the more confined your sphere of observation, the more perfect would be your remarks.
Or when Julia discovered the ancient life hidden in rocks.
This is the one we found this morning on the beach.
And...
JULIA GASPS Look at that!
There's your ammonite.
And what happened when Adam came face-to-face with the future of farming.
When you think of pig farming, you just think of, you know, smelly pigs and perhaps sausages and bacon, but this technology is just extraordinary.
Wytham Woods are owned by Oxford University.
There have been experiments going on here for 70 years.
The woods themselves sit just a few miles west of the city of Oxford.
It was in these woods that a scientist called Charles Elton made some of his most important discoveries.
He had a lifelong passion for national history, and his work here in the 1940s and '50s put the science of ecology on the map.
Today, people like Clive Hambler are following in his footsteps, often with nothing more high-tech than water and a nozzle.
What I'm trying to do is see if I can find any spiders' webs, and the easiest way to do it is often to make them stand out when they're covered in mist.
Why are you looking for the spiders and their webs?
Because it turns out that these dead plant stems are often teeming with life, and this is one of Charles Elton's great insights.
That the dead material is more important than living material to many of the organisms here.
So many people think that animals depend very much on green plants, but in fact, they often depend on them when they're dead.
Back in the 1940s, these ideas were revolutionary.
They sealed Elton's reputation as the foremost ecologist of his day.
His was a different way of looking at the world, which is still throwing up challenging ideas.
Wildlife often depends on having a very large amount of surface to live on, and it needs a damp environment to live in, so a physically complex thing like a tree, a conifer tree, with lots of little needles, provides a home for lots of wildlife.
And so conifers are actually amongst our best habitats for many types of animal.
A lot of people don't particularly like conifers.
We have plantations of them which get chopped down and people don't want to put any more in their place.
Absolutely.
But, if you look at the habitats in Britain that have the most animals and most species per square metre, it's conifer woodland, not oak woodland.
So, this is the kind of inheritance of Elton, to make people think again about...
That's right.
..About what are often dismissed as, you know, unnecessary things in the countryside?
I mean, he started to look at the world from a very general ecological point of view, so he looked at these structures, he looked at the temperature and the rainfall and the moisture in the air, and he realised that all those things come together, and an animal has its niche, or a plant has its niche, which is how it fits into the ecosystem.
And one of Elton's great insights was really understanding what a niche was, and defining what a niche was.
Charles Elton continued his work in Wytham Woods right up until the late-1960s.
His ideas set the tone for scientific study of the environment, and brought about a revolution in thinking about our landscape.
Just as, over a century earlier, there had been another huge shift in scientific thinking.
But that wasn't down to academia.
It was down to an ordinary girl with an extraordinary passion, as Julia found out when she went to Dorset.
To the seaside town of Lyme Regis, the home of British fossil hunting.
This beach on the outskirts of town is one of the best places in the world to find fossils.
It's jam-packed with them.
They're all around me!
These cliffs were created by layers of sediment, deposited 150 to 200 million years ago, trapping dead sea creatures and preserving them as fossils.
Anyone's allowed to pick up fossils from the beach, but it's easier with a guide, like fossil hunter Paddy Howe from the Lyme Regis Museum.
So, what are we looking for along here?
I'm looking for stones that might have ammonites inside.
They're flat, grey, fairly smooth.
The edges are either almost sharp like that, or they're flat.
They're not rounded, like most pebbles.
What we can do is split the stone...
Expertly done!
Well, there is a small one inside.
Oh, yes, a little baby one!
I was hoping for something better than that.
Right.
But, er...
Are going to throw this back to the ocean?
I'll leave that one, and we'll see if we can find some more.
Come on, then.
Absolutely nothing.
No!
Rubbish!
What kind of a fossil hunter are you?!
'Mmm, maybe it's not so easy after all.
'Oh, well, try again.'
Oh, another?
Oh!
Next!
'Oh, hold on!
'180 million years of history in an instant.'
I'm quite happy with that.
That one's going to be quite nice there.
This one, this one.
And these ones, we can potentially clean up.
So you could clean those up and make them brighter and...?
Yeah, absolutely.
More attractive?
I reckon, yeah.
While Paddy polishes up my fossils, I'm going back 200 years, to when Lyme Regis earned its nickname, Fossil Town.
It began with a kind of Indiana Jones in a bonnet - Mary Anning.
She scoured the beaches and cliffs, collecting fossils to sell to wealthy summer visitors.
In 1811, Mary's brother spotted a skull protruding out of a cliff, and over the following months, Mary proceeded to dig out an almost entire skeleton of an ancient crocodile creature.
She was just 12 years old.
Mary sold it for £23 - about £1,000 in today's money.
There is a replica in the Lyme Regis Museum.
The creature was eventually named an ichthyosaur, and this is what it would have looked like 200 million years ago, swimming in Lyme Bay.
'Like most geologists, 'Tom Sharpe from Cardiff Museum is a Mary Anning fan.'
Do you think she has genuinely influenced fossil hunters today and geologists today?
I mean, she was a great tourist attraction in her own right, in her own time.
People came to Lyme Regis to go fossil hunting with Mary Anning.
And you look around you today, there are fossil shops here in Lyme Regis, and there are collectors here, carrying on the tradition of Mary Anning.
She made some significant discoveries during her time, didn't she?
Oh, yes, she did.
I mean, she really transformed our view of life in the Jurassic sea, 200 million years ago.
She was finding some remarkable creatures, which no-one had ever seen before, and finding complete examples as well.
And she was finding these things at just the right time, when geology was becoming established as a science.
So, she was certainly born at the right time, but she was a woman - was she born the right sex?
No, she wasn't, really.
And she wasn't the right class either.
We forget, really, how strongly stratified - almost as well stratified as the rocks are round here - British society was 200 years ago.
There was no opportunity for her to move up the social scale.
She'd probably be one of the world's leading palaeontologists if she were alive today.
She found the first long-necked plesiosaur and a flying dinosaur, the pterodactyl.
In 1830, renowned geologist Henry De la Beche imagined the seas and skies populated by Mary's creatures.
She became so well known, her work is said to have inspired the tongue twister, "She sells seashells on the seashore".
My fossil may not be up to Mary's standard, but I'm hoping that Paddy's been able to clean it up.
It's the big moment.
This is the one we found this morning on the beach.
There's your ammonite.
That is lovely!
'I'm quite impressed with that.
'But it's small fry,' compared to this.
An ammonite pavement.
A fossil graveyard made up of hundreds of squid-like creatures that lived in shells.
Sadly, it's slowly disintegrating.
Richard Edmonds from the Jurassic Coast team is trying to find out why.
Over the last few years, I've noticed there's been some really weird movements down here, ledges pushing and graunching and breaking.
Why do you think it is shifting so?
We really don't know at the moment.
It's a bit of a mystery, but we're not seeing it anywhere else along the Jurassic Coast.
And is it something that we should be worried about?
I mean, this will be gone one day?
No, I mean, this coast is a product of erosion.
If it wasn't eroding and changing, it wouldn't be the place it is.
We may lose quite a lot of this ammonite pavement, but then, some more of it will appear somewhere else, and we've just got to live with that fact.
It's the nature of this coastline.
And that's where Richard's team have gone high-tech, and called in Greg Colley with his helicopter camera.
We got some funding from Natural England to fly this helicopter with a camera at really high resolution to make a photomontage, you know, a baseline survey, so that I can come back and actually see what's actually happening, how this beach is changing through time.